Finding Aid for International Center (University of Michigan) records, 1927-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
International Center (University of Michigan) records 1927-2002, 1933-1976
University of Michigan. International Center.
21 linear feet
87207 Bimu C460 2
The records of the University of Michigan International Center contain administrative records from the various Directors of the center. These materials include documentation on the establishment of the University of Michigan's foreign student exchange scholarships, records relating to the development of important programs and national associations for international students, housing surveys between 1965-1971, printed materials such as annual reports, newsletters, and manuals, scrapbooks, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the International Center have been received in various accessions, 1944 to 1991 (Donor # 1932 ). Additional records were received in 2005 and 2014.
The collection is unrestricted.
The University of Michigan was a pioneer in the development of guidance and counseling programs for its many foreign students. Instrumental in the early efforts of helping these students adjust to their new condition was J. Raleigh Nelson. In 1908, Nelson had come to the University of Michigan to head up a program of English language instruction for engineering students; in 1911, he was named Counselor to Foreign Students in the College of Engineering.
For many years, the counseling of foreign students was largely limited to the College of Engineering. In 1933, President Ruthven, aware of the need in other schools, asked Nelson to serve as University Counselor to Foreign Students. In this broader role, Nelson looked about for a centralized meeting place where the university's foreign students could gather, discuss common problems, and enjoy each other's company. Space at the Michigan Union was suggested, and in August 1938, Nelson (now Director of the International Center) moved into his new quarters. Within this one office, Nelson consolidated the responsibilities relating to foreign students which had formerly been spread throughout the University: English instruction, liaison with the government over immigration and naturalization problems, and coordinating programs of social and intellectual enrichment.
During his tenure, Nelson and the International Center promoted social contacts between American and foreign students on campus. The social, political, religious, and economic leaders of Ann Arbor were also encouraged to attend and support activities sponsored by the International Center. One of Professor Nelson's last acts before his retirement in 1943 was to recommend the establishment of the International Center's Board of Governors. This insured continuity with regard to the direction and goals of the Center.
Dr. Esson M. Gale became director of the International Center in 1943. In 1927 he served as a visiting lecturer of Far Eastern history at the University of Michigan. He returned, in 1942, as James Orin Murfin Professor of Political Science. Gale brought to the Center a deep knowledge of the peoples and cultures of the Far East, having lived in China for over thirty years. During Gale's tenure the responsibilities of the director and the International Center increased to include the coordination of the growing international interests of the university. These included private and government sponsored foreign student exchange programs; the creation of government programs, e.g. the Advisory Board for Emergency Aid to Chinese Students; and the foreign visitors programs.
Dr. James M. Davis succeeded Dr. Gale in 1954 as director of the International Center. He also held the position of assistant professor of education at the University of Michigan. Prior to coming to Michigan, Davis worked at the Institute of International Education in New York and from 1948 to 1954 was Counselor to Foreign Students and Executive Director of the Foundation for International Understanding Through Students at the University of Washington in Seattle.
In his ten years as director, Davis stressed the importance of counseling. The size of the staff increased allowing greater contact between individual students and staff members. Surveys and projects, e.g. the annual housing survey, gave the staff additional information to support their counseling. Davis also urged the foreign students to participate and accept greater responsibilities in campus activities. This was accomplished through the International Students Association. Under the direction of the International Center, the Association became the major voice representing foreign students on campus.
Dr. Robert B. Klinger, a member of the International Center staff since 1938, became acting director of the Center in 1964 and director in 1966. Dr. Klinger continued the policies established by his predecessors; in addition, he developed programs aimed at strengthening the ties of the International Center to its foreign student alumni. Under his guidance, the International Center also offered greater services for those American students interested in studying and traveling abroad. Klinger left the International Center in 1971.
Today the International Center continues to provide such services as non-academic counseling for foreign students, arranging programs for visiting foreign leaders, providing information on housing, health insurance, employment, and legal information, advising student groups, and representing the University of Michigan in the relationships with various governmental and private agencies.
The collection is divided into six series. The first series, Historical Files, contains early filing methods of the Directors and a small amount of background on the Center. It also contains early papers from 1927-1930 on the Cosmopolitan Club and spring trips for foreign students. The second series, Director's Files, has been organized according to the filing systems employed by each of the Center's first four directors: J. Raleigh Nelson (1933-1943); Esson M. Gale (1943-1954); James M. Davis (1954-1964); and Robert B. Klinger (1964-1971). Files of each director comprise separate sub-series. Each of these four sub-series includes administrative records such as papers of the Board of Governors, minutes of committees connected to the International Center, and annual reports. Within each sub-series there are files of particular importance and interest. Photographs compose the third series, including one scrapbook of directors, students, and visitors to the International Center. Printed materials comprise the fourth series. The fifth series is made up of newspaper clippings. The sixth series consists of National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Publications).
Subjects:
National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (U.S.); University of Michigan--Students.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gale, Esson M. (Esson McDowell), 1884-1964; Japan.; Korea.
Contributors:
Davis, James McCoy, 1914-; Gale, Esson M. (Esson McDowell), 1884-1964; Klinger, Robert B., 1914-; Nelson, J. Raleigh (Joseph Raleigh)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Historical Files
  - Histories and Outlines of Director's Files (Box 1)
  - Early Papers (Box 1)
- Director's Files
  - 1933-1943 (J. Raleigh Nelson Executive Director)
    The records of the International Center under J. Raleigh Nelson (1933-1943) contain documents that relate to the establishment of the University of Michigan's foreign student exchange scholarships. These various programs include the Barbour Scholarships for Oriental Women, Latin American Exchanges, the Lingnan Scholarships, and the agreement with the American University of Beirut, Lebanon.
    - Academic Records and Files (Box 1)
    - Alumni Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Barbour Scholars (Box 1)
    - Blakeman, Edward (Box 1)
    - Board of Governors (Box 1)
    - Cabinet and Staff (Box 1)
    - Chinese Activities (Box 1)
    - Coordinators Office (Box 1)
    - Committee on Intercultural Relations (Box 1)
    - Committee on Postwar International Education (Box 1)
    - Deputations (Box 1)
    - Exchange Scholarships-American University of Beirut (Box 1)
    - Experiment in International Living (Box 1)
    - Foreign Student Committee of the Ann Arbor Friends (Box 1)
    - Foreign Women (Box 1)
    - Hurrey, Charles D. (Box 1)
    - Immigration Reports (Box 1)
    - Institute of International Education (Box 1)
    - International Club (Box 1)
    - International Council (Box 1)
    - International Dinner (Box 1)
    - International Directories (Box 1)
    - International Education Conferences (Box 1)
    - International Houses (Box 1)
    - International Night (Box 1)
    - International Programs (Box 1)
    - International Residence (Box 1)
    - International Student Movement (Box 1)
    - Japanese Attaches (Box 1)
    - Jones, Dr. Thomas (Box 1)
    - Kellogg Institute (Box 1)
    - La Sociedad Latina Americana (Box 1)
    - Latin-American Relations, Committee on (Box 1)
    - Latin-American Students (Box 1)
    - Latin-American Summer Session (Box 1)
    - Latin-American Visitors (Box 1)
    - Lingnan Scholarships (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - National Youth Administration (Box 1)
    - New Education Fellowship Conference (Box 1)
    - Nisei (Box 1)
    - O (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - P (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - President's Receptions, Correspondence (Box 1)
    - R (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - ReDortsto the Council (Box 1)
    - Rufus, Prof. (Box 1)
    - Russian Students Fund (Box 1)
    - Scholarships (Box 1)
    - Speakers (Box 1)
    - State Department, Visitors (Box 1)
    - Student Christian Association (Box 1)
    - Summer Camps, Seminars (Box 1)
    - T (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Tours (Box 1)
    - U (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - W (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Weekly Calendar (Box 1)
    - Winter "Summer School" (Box 1)
    - X-Y-Z (Miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Executive Director's Files 1933-1943 (Gale and Davis)
    The second sub-series (1943-1961) is the filing system established by Esson M. Gale and continued by James M. Davis. Under the directorship of Gale and Davis several important programs and national associations were established at the University of Michigan. The documents in this sub-series reflect the development of the University of Michigan's English Language Institute, the International Student Association, and the university's involvement in the Peace Corps. In addition, there are records concerning the Chinese Aid Program and the National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (NAFSA), an organization founded in Ann Arbor in 1948. The NAFSA records include administrative records from 1948 to 1958. These are the most complete set of records available for this time period as the records belonging to NAFSA were accidentally destroyed at their headquarters. The National Association of Foreign Student Advisers was renamed the National Association of Foreign Student Affairs in 1964, and again renamed NAFSA: Association of International Educators in 1990.
    - Administration and Administrative Committees
      - Admission and Committees on Admission (Box 2)
      - Advisers, Committees of (Box 2)
      - Bills and Receipts, General (Box 2)
      - Board of Governors 1942-1962, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Committee on Intercultural Relations 1946-1959, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - English Language Institute 1945-1961, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - English Language Service (Box 2)
      - Expansion and Development Council (Box 2)
      - Lewis, Vice-President and President, Vice Presidents (Box 3)
      - Madelon Pound House (Box 3)
      - Office Orders (Box 3)
      - Procedures and Replies to Queries re (Box 3)
      - Reports to President, Senate, Fifield Committee
        - Annual Reports 1936-1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Reports
        - Career Patterns of Foreign Students Who Received the Ph.D. from the University of Michigan 1941-1961 (Box 3)
        - Committee of Interim Council for Community Services to International Visitors (Box 3)
        - The Function and Scope of International Affairs at the University of Michigan (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous 1938-1955 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous 1955-1962 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous, no dates (Box 3)
      - Research Projects and Articles for Publication (Box 3)
      - Staff, Appointments to, and Meetings 1949-1953, 1958-1961, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Staff, Promotion Recommendations (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan Conferences and Committees
        - Commission on International Relations in Education (Box 3)
        - Consuls' Day, October 25,1956 (Box 3)
        - Institute on College and University Administration 1959 (Box 3)
        - Japanese American Conference 1953 (Box 3)
        - Pelz Committee 1955 (Box 3)
        - Schoolmaster's Conference 1961 (Box 3)
    - Alumni
      - Correspondence, General (Box 3)
      - Foreign Alumni through 1937 (Box 3)
      - Trainee Study E3-263 (Box 3)
      - Technical Cooperation Administration (Box 3)
    - Bureaus and Offices-Federal
      - Congress (Box 3)
      - Office of Education (Box 3)
      - State Department
        - The Foreign Student in the United States (Box 3)
        - Correspondence 1944-1961, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Other US Departments and Agencies (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
        - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO (Box 4)
      - Peace Corps
        - General (Box 4)
        - International Youth Service (Box 4)
        - Proposals: Returning Peace Corps Volunteer Program (Box 4)
    - Bureaus and Offices-Foreign
      - African (Box 4)
      - Asia Foundation and Committee on Free Asia (Box 4)
      - Asian Affairs, National Council (Box 4)
      - Chinese
        - ARCI (Box 4)
        - Chinese American Cultural Relation (Box 4)
        - General (Box 4)
      - European (Box 4)
      - Indian (Box 4)
      - Iraqi (Box 4)
      - Latin American (Box 4)
      - Near East Foundation (Box 4)
      - Turkish (Box 4)
    - Bureau and Offices-American Private
      - American Personnel and Guidance Association (Box 4)
      - American Council 3-of Learned Societies (Box 4)
      - American Council on Education (Box 4)
      - American Friends Service Committee (Box 4)
      - Committee of Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students (Box 4)
      - Common Council for American Unity (Box 4)
      - Council on Student Travel
        - General (Box 4)
        - Bogota Conference 1962 (Box 4)
      - Experiment in International Living (Box 4)
      - Ford Foundation (Box 4)
      - International Development Conference (Box 4)
      - Institute of International Education
        - Fourth National Conference of Exchange of Persons (Box 4)
        - General Correspondence 1946-1961, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (General) (Box 5)
        - Background and Histories (Box 5)
        - Directories 1959, 1961 (Box 5)
        - Foreign Student Advisor's Bookshelf (Box 5)
      - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Committees)
        - Bibliography Project (Box 5)
        - Development and Planning Committee 1958-1959, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Government Liaison Committee (Box 5)
        - Government Regulations Roundtable (Box 5)
        - Membership Committee (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous Committees (Box 5)
        - Publications Committee (Box 5)
        - Research and Survey Committee 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Session on Research (Box 5)
        - Three, Committee of (Box 5)
      - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (National)
        - Papers
          - General 1942, 1946-1960, 18 folders (Box 6)
          - General 1942, 1946-1960, 18 folders (Box 7)
            - Board of Directors 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Regional)
        - Papers 1953-1957, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - National Association of Student Personnel Administrators 1955 (Box 7)
      - National Student Association (Box 7)
      - Council for Community Services to International Visitors (Box 7)
      - Williamsburg Assembly (Box 7)
      - International House Association (Box 7)
      - Inter-University Commission on Travel Grants (Box 7)
      - American Association of Land Colleges and Universities (Box 7)
      - Program for Community Development Training (Box 7)
    - Colleges and Universities Abroad
      - Libraries Abroad (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous Universities Abroad (Box 7)
      - Committee on International House and Center (Box 7)
    - Community Services-Ann Arbor
      - Junior Chamber of Commerce (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Protestant Foundation (Box 7)
      - Rotary (Box 7)
    - Community Services-Outside Ann Arbor
      - Community Organization (Box 7)
      - Home Visitations (Box 7)
      - Student Speeches (Box 7)
      - Tours (Box 8)
      - Visits to Farms (Box 8)
    - Other Universities and Colleges
      - Foreign Student Advisors (Box 8)
      - Michigan State University (Box 8)
    - Legal
      - Immigration
        - Attorneys (Box 8)
        - Deportation Cases, General (Box 8)
        - Detroit, General Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Exchange Visitors (Box 8)
        - Laws and Pamphlets (Box 8)
        - Washington and St. Paul, Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Committee on Immigration (Box 8)
      - Income Tax (Box 8)
      - Selective Service (Box 8)
    - Library (Box 8)
    - Personnel
      - Biographical Information on Directors (Box 8)
      - Esson M. Gale (Box 8)
      - Sarah Grollman (Box 8)
    - Programs, Social and Recreational
      - Christmas Parties (Box 8)
      - International Ball (Box 8)
      - International Students Day (Box 8)
      - International Week and Pageants (Box 8)
      - Orientation (Box 9)
      - Receptions and Special Events (Box 9)
      - Thanksgiving (Box 9)
    - Publications and Publicity
      - Directories (Box 9)
      - Directories-Chinese (Box 9)
      - International Center-Pamphlets (Box 9)
      - Newsletters, Bulletins (Box 9)
    - Scholarships and Fellowships
      - Barbour Scholarships (Box 9)
      - Foreign Governments-General (Box 9)
      - Foundations and companies (Box 9)
      - Michigan Press Club (Box 9)
      - Phoenix (Box 9)
      - Private (Box 9)
      - State Department (Box 9)
      - Michigan. University; Committee on Foreign Student Scholarships
        - General Papers 1947-1961, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Marshall Scholarship Committee
        - British Exchange Program (Box 9)
        - Free University of Berlin (Box 9)
        - German Exchange Program (Box 9)
        - Hungarian (Box 9)
        - Guatemalan (Box 9)
        - Soviet Student Exchange 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Beirut Exchange (Box 10)
        - Brazilian Exchange (Box 10)
    - Schools and Colleges of U of M: Special Correspondence
      - Dentistry and Post Graduate (Box 10)
      - Graduate (Box 10)
      - Law (Box 10)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts (Box 10)
      - Medical and Post Graduate (Box 10)
      - Natural Resources (Box 10)
      - Public Health (Box 10)
      - Engineering (Box 10)
      - Other Schools and Colleges (Box 10)
    - Statistics of Foreign Students 1938-1961, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Students-Groups and Clubs
      - African (Box 10)
      - Arab (Box 10)
      - Asians, in General (Iraqi) (Box 10)
      - Asians, Southeast (not Thailand) (Box 10)
      - Chinese
        - Societies (Box 10)
        - Stranded and Relief 1938-1945 (Box 10)
        - ECA, Second Grant (Box 10)
        - ECA, Third Grant (Box 10)
      - Indian, Pakistani (Box 10)
      - International Students Association and Predecessors 1947-1952, 1956-1960, 7 folders (Box 11)
      - Iranians (Box 11)
      - Israeli (Box 11)
      - Japanese (Box 11)
      - Korean (Box 11)
      - Latin American (Box 11)
      - Siamese (Box 11)
      - Student Government Council (Box 11)
      - Student Religious Association (Box 11)
      - Turkish (Box 11)
      - Servicemen; Displaced Persons (Box 11)
      - Mexican (Box 11)
      - Hungarians (Box 11)
    - Student Relations
      - Academic: Certificates of Attendance; Transcripts (Box 11)
      - Disciplinary (Box 11)
      - Housing
        - Friends Center (Box 11)
        - International House 1945-1959, 4 folders (Box 11)
        - Residence Halls (Box 11)
        - Rooming Houses (Box 11)
        - Survey (Box 11)
        - Transient (Box 11)
      - Illness (Box 11)
      - Insurance (Box 11)
    - Practical Training
      - Research and Evaluation (Box 11)
      - Women (Box 11)
    - Visitors
      - General (Box 11)
      - Indian (Box 11)
      - U.S. State Department (Box 11)
      - Faculty and Researchers (Box 11)
    - Chinese Aid Program
      - Loans and Certification (Box 11)
      - Announcements, General and policies (Box 11)
      - Scholars and Researchers (Box 11)
      - Visits and conferences in Ann Arbor (Box 11)
      - Chinese Students Clubs Loans and Action (Box 11)
      - Medical Problems and Announcements (Box 11)
      - Immigration Law and Employment (Box 11)
      - News Items (Box 11)
      - Statistics, Surveys, and Analysis of CAP (Box 11)
      - Transportation items (Box 11)
      - University Financial Reports on Chinese Aid (Box 11)
      - Letters from State Department 1953-1955, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1962-1965 (James M. Davis Executive Directors)
    The third sub-series contains documents from the second filing system used by James M. Davis. Davis, in 1962, modified the system established by Esson M. Gale and used this revised system through 1965. The documents in this group mirror Dr. Davis' and the International Center's work with private American agencies and bureaus, e.g. the Council on Student Travel and the National Council for Community Services to International Visitors (COSERV). In addition, the actions of the International Students Association are well documented here.
    - Accounts (Box 12)
    - Administration, International Center
      - Anniversary (Box 12)
      - Annual Reports 1961-1962, 1964-1965 (Box 12)
      - Board of Governors 1961-1965, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - General papers (Box 12)
      - University Committee on Student Counseling Services (Box 12)
    - Agencies and Bureaus (Federal Government)
      - Department of State (Box 12)
      - Agency for International Development (Box 12)
      - Immigration and Naturalization Service (Box 12)
      - Other Agencies (Box 12)
    - Agencies and Bureaus (American Private)
      - A-Z (Box 12)
      - Council on Student Travel 1961, 1963-1964, 3 folders
        - Japanese programs (Box 13)
        - World University Service (Box 13)
      - National Council for Community Services to International Visitors (COSERV) 1960-1964, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Experiment in International Living (Box 13)
      - Institute of International Education (Box 13)
      - Other Agencies
        - Advisory Committee (Box 13)
        - African-American Institute (Box 13)
        - Comparative Education Society (Box 13)
        - Creole Foundation (Box 13)
        - Michigan Cooperative Curriculum Program (Box 13)
        - Phi Delta Kappa (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous Agencies (Box 13)
    - Alumni (Box 13)
    - Colleges and Schools-University of Michigan (Box 13)
    - Colleges and Universities-American (Box 13)
    - Community Services-Ann Arbor
      - American National Red Cross (Box 13)
      - Community Services and Social Activities Available to Wives of International Students and Faculty (Box 13)
      - General papers (Box 13)
      - Protestant Foundation 1961-1965, 2 folders (Box 13)